Hello, and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today
we're going to be learning how to
cyclize ketones and aldehydes with
an alcohol group on the same chain.
Now when this happens, we'll be making
a hemiacetal and a hemiketal, which
will then go to a secondary reaction
creating an acetal and a ketal.
Now when this happens, there's
a very stereotypical thing that
we're going to be looking at.
Um, this reaction is kind of like
when a snake bites its own tail, and
when we cyclize these, they form a
very specific functional group here.
So this is a hemiacetal.
Notice how both oxygens are attached to
the same carbon, which is a chiral carbon.
or an anomeric carbon.
The way I always like to remember
these, it's like a pair of googly eyes
attached to the exact same carbon.
Um, now with this one down
here, this is a hemiketal, and
so what is the key difference?
Well, with a hemiacetal, that
started as an aldehyde, which
has a -CHO group, right?
An H that's on here, and you can see it
like a little tail that's sticking out.
Now the hemiketal, this is a, this
started as a ketone, so you can see
the carbons on both sides of it,
and it gets split into two oxygens.
In this particular video, we're going to
go step by step how to do this reaction.
And we will break it down so
that way you can repeat this
in your, in your introductory
organic and biochemistry course.
I hope that this video helps and let's
look at the process of how to do this.
The first thing that we need to
do is determine what the size of
our cyclic ring is going to be.
So typically what you are going to
get is a chain that looks like this.
So we can see that we have an aldehyde
here, where it is a five carbon chain with
an alcohol somewhere close to the end.
So whenever we get a chain like this,
the way that we need to do is we want
to start our numbering at the carbonyl.
So that's C double bond O.
And with this numbering scheme,
this is not a way to number it, but
we're just trying to see how many
different members of our ring are
we going to make, being that this is
going to make a heterocyclic ring.
So one that's going to have an oxygen
embedded in it, like with it as an ether.
We're going to stop the numbering at
the oxygen that is on the alcohol.
So like I mentioned before, we're going
to start it at the carbonyl, right?
So that's going to be number one.
Then we have number two, three, four,
five, and then we're going to stop
it right on the alcohol on the oxygen
because that's going to be a member
of our new ring once we make it.
All right, let's look at our next step.
Alright, so our second step, the
whole idea here is now that we have
this thing numbered, we need to line
up the functional groups because
this is what's going to be showing
the exact reaction because we want
to create a heterocyclic group.
So when this thing lines up, we
want to make it so that way the
alcohol is on opposite sides of
the carbon and then the oxygen is
on opposite sides of the hydrogen.
One way for you to think about this is
if you go back to electronegativity,
intermolecular forces, right?
The oxygen is delta minus,
hydrogen is delta plus.
So minus plus.
Same idea down here, right?
Minus plus.
So we want to line up the parts that are
going to be attracted to each other, kind
of making a indirect intermolecular force.
Between both of these different bonds
because this is what's going to lead
it to the actual reaction So now let's
take a look at trying to cyclize these
so we what we will do is we're going to
take this like I mentioned we're going
to take that C double bond O and We are
going to line it up with the oxygen from
the other side and I'm going to try to
color code these as we go So we have
C=O, and we're going to line it up with
-OH from our two parts of our group.
Now, we are going to keep our numbering,
so this was number 1, this was number 6.
Now, the whole idea here is, as
we're cyclizing it, we want it
to look like a ring structure.
So, what is a 6 member ring?
Well, a 6 member ring
looks like a hexagon.
So, ultimately, we want our ring
to either have a hexagon, or maybe
a pentagon, is usually the shapes.
It's usually 6 or 5.
are the typical shapes for this reaction.
So, let's start it.
So we have 1, then it goes down to
CH2, which is going to be our second
position, then another CH2, which is
our third position, so let's number
those, 2, 3, then we have CH2, which
is 4, and then CH2, which is 5.
And then we'll connect.
We want to show how that thing
is going to be bending, um, and
have the numbering so that way you
can follow along and keep track.
And as I mentioned before, right, we're
going to be showing this interaction
that is here, um, between these different
groups, because this is where the reaction
is going to be taking place between them.
Let's go on to the next step.
All right, so with this particular
step, now that we have our structure
that we made earlier, What we're
going to be doing is the snake
is going to bite its own tail.
So meaning that if you think of
the ketone as, or the ketone or
the aldehyde as the head, right?
So we're gonna color code that,
um, where it's going to be
biting the hydrogen portion.
So we're going to break two
bonds, and then we're going
to form two bonds as a result.
So break two, form two.
So what we're going to see here is,
well, what bonds are we going to break?
Well, this is all about how
are the functional groups
reacting with each other.
So we're going to break apart
of each functional group.
So we have a little red X on one of
the bonds in each functional group.
So we take out one from the double bond.
One from the alcohol now, we're going to
be making two bonds as a result So if you
remember before I use these green dots
where we're going to be joining at those
green dots so we break to form two now in
the process what's going to be happening
is the Alcohol is going to turn into an
ether and the aldehyde or ketone is going
to turn into an alcohol Now, after, once
this reaction occurs, this is officially
your hemiacetal or your hemiketal.
Down here I drew our little bonds
that we had on our structure.
So remember we're going to break
two and we're going to form two.
So let's take this and we're
going to move it to the side.
So once those break.
What we will do is we're going to erase
them and we're going to now make two
actual bonds where the green dots were.
So as you can see here, we have
what is now an alcohol and an ether
that have formed in the structure.
After this reaction
has taken place, right?
Because if you look at the original,
we had an aldehyde and then an alcohol.
So things have changed.
The different groups
change in the structure.
So this is a cyclic ring shape.
We can clean this up a
little bit for ourselves too.
So if we take this, what
are we going to have?
Well, we can show that C O H, just to kind
of label those little functional groups.
We can show how the other ether is
going to be in the chain as well.
And then we can connect
every other little bit.
And one thing I kind of noticed here
is that we were actually missing
a hydrogen in all of this as well.
So there's a little hydrogen tail
that kind of got lost in our original
structures as we went through.
So there should be a hydrogen
tail whenever we have a
hemiacetal or a hemiketal too.
So let's make sure we have that
in our final structure, right?
So that's how you can tell,
is it, which one do we have?
So we have our CH2, CH2,
and then our CH2, CH2.
Or, if you want to draw it
like a fancy ring, you can.
So this is what it would look like.
Right, is, is it both has a
geometric and a condensed.
Okay, so we have our skeletal
structure, or geometric, and then
we have our condensed structure.
Alright, now what is our next step?
Well, this is where we made a hemiacetal.
So the same exact reaction would
occur if you do a hemiketal.
We'll show that in this video as well.
I'll do an example of that.
Um, so let's take a look at the final
step if you want to make this an acetal.
Step four, hemiacetals and
hemiketals are unstable due to
the presence of alcohol groups.
So the last thing is, so the alcohol
that we originally had turned into an
ether, that does not react any further.
But the alcohol group that is
on our ring structure That is
going to react to make an ether.
So we're going to have two
ethers on our final structure.
Now the way this happens is
through a condensation reaction.
So we're going to remove water
by reacting with another alcohol
group to stabilize itself.
Now, where is this reaction most
common with, is if you, when we go
into carbohydrates, carbohydrates
will do this by making chains of
carbohydrates, so making, uh, polymers
of these different carbohydrates.
So, when this happens, this
is how polysaccharides and
disaccharides form, where multiple
rings will react with each other.
But we're gonna do this reaction
just with a simple alcohol, like a,
maybe a methanol or an isopropyl.
So we're gonna be removing this.
So in this reaction, we're gonna
continue this with the addition of
a two propanol or isopropyl alcohol.
So how this does this exactly work?
Well, we've done on this channel
multiple times in the past, condensation.
So when we do this, we're going
to take a, the other alcohol.
So we're gonna take our ho.
And being that this is isopropyl
alcohol, we will put our little
isopropyl group like so, and here
we'll put it over here as well.
So it's CH with CH3CH3.
Now the whole idea with this
is you're going to be removing
water to condense it down.
So when this happens, we're
going to be removing H2O.
So we can see H.
H2O from this structure, and we're
going to be removing all these pieces.
Now when this happens we're
going to be taking that off.
So let's just remove that like so.
We're going to put that to the side.
So H2O is a product, and we're going
to be connecting our rings together.
So now what we're going to be having.
It's like a little antenna that's
going to be attached to the top of
our different ring structures like so.
So this is what we refer to as a
acetal, and it's going to be the
same type of reaction with a ketal.
It'll be another alcohol or potentially
another ring group that's going to be
used to attach the two pieces together.
So this is how we can do
these types of reactions.
Um, it, we're going to be
doing another example using a
ketal or hemiketal this time.
So let's go through it, go through
another example so you can see it
done with both types of structures.
And I'll go through some tips on
how to do it that way as well.
With this question, what we will be
doing is demonstrating the formation
of a hemiketal with 7 hydroxy.
Three he known or a
ketone with an alcohol.
The very first step that we're going
to be doing is we're going to be
determining the size of our cyclic group.
So, the first thing that we did last
time is we started our numbering
from our carbonyl and going all
the way to our alcohol, including
the oxygen in our structure.
So you can see here that we have six
different things that are being numbered
and we ended it at the alcohol group.
starting at the carbonyl.
And one thing you're going to
notice that at carbon one, we're
going to have a little arm that's
going to be attached to it, right?
We don't want to lose any
carbons throughout here.
So keep in mind there are still eight,
there's still seven carbons on this chain.
So we need to make sure that
they're all accounted for here.
So you can see that we numbered
up the five for the carbons,
but we want to show our Hemi.
Group.
So now what we're going to be doing with
this structure is we want to, to line
up our two functional groups to help
illustrate how this ring is going to be.
Now this is where one of my tips comes in.
So the first thing is when you're lining
this up, we have our C double bond
O and then our O H just like before,
but notice something different, right?
This double bond oxygen is
not on the end of the chain.
So we need to kind of be a little
careful here about making sure
we include all of our carbons.
So we want to, with this one, we want to
like kind of break our geometry rules.
Let's write the ethyl so that's
hanging off of the side and it's just
going to be kind of awkwardly there,
but we want to keep track of it.
We don't want to lose it.
So this is still going
to be carbon number one.
This was going to be our
oxygen was number six.
So we are going to start our structure.
So we go to two, three,
four, five, And six.
All right, and let's number them so that
we can follow all of those little pieces.
All right, so now that we have
that, we lined up our groups.
So what we are going to do now
is in step three, we're going to
actually have the reaction occur.
So if you remember, we break
two bonds, we form two bonds.
So when we zoom in on this guy, we're
going to break one of each of these
different bonds, and we're going to
be making a bond happen between our
carbon and our oxygen and our oxygen
or hydrogen to make our two groups.
So when this occurs, we will be
making our different, our little
hemi, our hemi group, which
will be our final reaction here.
So let's erase all of our little numbers.
So we're going to be making our
ether, breaking our double bond
and our original alcohol, and
making an alcohol just like this.
So this will be your final structure.
We can clean it, we can clean it up for
ourselves, just so that we can see exactly
what this thing is going to look like.
So we're going to have
our six member ring.
Right, and it's going to have an
alcohol embedded in, or sorry,
an ether embedded in the ring.
And this reaction can do another step.
So if it was something that let, if we
added another alcohol to it, It could go
through and do another step to it, but
this one we're just going to stop for the
matter of time, stop at the hemiketal.
So this is how a hemiketal is formed.
I hope that this video helped showing
how the snake can bite its own tail.
We're always changing just
the functional groups.
Um, notice also here, just
to kind of point out that we
still have our chiral carbon.
So you can see how
there's all carbons there.
There's no hydrogen hiding unlike the
hemiacetal one There's a little hydrogen
tail so you can see that difference I
hope this video helped you Please use it
to the best that you can to help you with
homeworks or quizzes or exams and I look
forward to seeing you In future videos.
I hope you all have a wonderful day Please
hit that like and subscribe button to keep
supporting the channel and I look and I
look forward to seeing you in the future
All right now, I'll see you all later.
Bye now